all right hello everyone welcome back
it's our second discussion on chapter n
so we can look at the
chapter and look at previous questions
but before we do so does anyone just
want to give any general comment or
thought or question on
nine
like any section of nine that was
interesting or
any
topic sorry I'm running a bit behind in
the reading so uh haven't looked at
chapter
n or or even
another
topic or another question if you want to
go to
it that's sorry
yeah
go for itna oh no I just I'm this is my
first time attending and I did not know
that we were going to be working on
chapter nine so now that I I'll be I'll
prepare but I was focusing uh I focus my
work mainly on making sure that I
understand some key
Concepts in the book and so so I'm not
really quite
ready
today oh it's all good thank you for
joining I
mean it's always listed here but also
it's kind of like we even talk about
things outside the textbook so we can
talk about whatever people
want even just the theme of chapter nine
with um modelbased data analysis I mean
this is the chapter where the models are
connected to empirical data that's
always a useful topic
or or just anything people want to talk
about or we can look at some prior
questions
I the only
thing just a really minor comment about
the book uh I just noticed that Parts
one and two are not don't have
labels on the index
page that's that's uh that's one thing
that I picked out bun um but like I said
I'm I'm new to this topic I will get I
will do a lot of reading this week but I
really wanted to make sure that I
understood where the free energy
principle concept came from so I'm
really way
behind so it's all good it's all good um
when you say part one and part two you
mean chapters 1 through five and chapter
6 through 10 uh well when I have the PDF
and on the PDF on the first on the index
page I not is that that Parts one and
two there no there's no label it just
has the list of the
sections like
this let me see part one and part two
part one and part
two
y on the on right on the in the content
page
yeah so the label the the label of the
labels of the parts are not in right on
included and I didn't know if that was
deliberate
or yeah I think the part one and part
two is just kind of like an
informal okay like the chapters are the
main
components
yeah um and if you want to know like for
the origin the fvp chapter 10 might give
you some
information oh good okay it's yeah okay
any other chapter 9 related topics um or
Andrew had some things to discuss or
anyone else could bring something
up yeah or go for it yes please
oh okay thanks Daniel thanks Angel um
yes I have a couple questions regarding
chapter uh
nine
um so
um I wonder how should I uh share with
please add them to the questions
everyone is just overwhelmingly
encouraged to add the written questions
to the
table
write questions uh in the table yeah
where make a blank
row and just put it into the question
part okay
okay um yeah let me um okay so I have to
go to this uh this website right to
share the
questions yeah you can follow like the
the you can click like the token for
active inference to follow to where I am
in chapter
nine yes I find chapter nine yeah so add
add the questions
there
okay okay then let me check if I'm on
the same page as you do yeah uh chapter
nine yeah yeah yeah I'm I'm there so so
okay okay so I just juggle between U so
first um I have a question regarding uh
regarding
equation
9.2 um so so what
is um this
Theta
Alpha in
equation 9.2 and simar writing
did you enter the question or where did
you write okay okay what is I'm gonna I
just copied it into there but yeah oh at
the wrong place okay no no it's okay
it's okay just this is how we can get
all the questions together what is Theta
Alpha so because it hasn't show up in
our previous you know chapters before
right this Theta Al sub
Alpha yes Theta sub Alpha yeah yeah okay
so um just to take a step back we're
using variational Lelo
approximation so what this technique is
doing is it's taking some distribution
it's going to find the central tendency
of it and then it's going to fit an
inverted Parabola over it and so that
could be a narrow paraba Parabola or it
could be a wide Parabola so that's the
variational Lao so it is a lot like kind
of fitting a gausian
approximation but of course a gaussian
has support everywhere and it continues
whereas a a parabola like just goes
down um so that's what the llas
approximation
does Theta is being used as commonly to
just refer to the total set of
parameters okay okay now
um down
here this is going to be in the context
of policy
selection so there's going to be beliefs
about action sequences we can take these
beliefs and calculate the average
probability of
pursuing an action
sequence so this is in the spirit of
pursuing action selection as a pure
statistical problem and finding the most
likely path path of least action not
appealing to any kind of like
intermediate reward function or anything
like that this requires us to distribute
the probability for each policy over the
actions implied by that
policy so the array U is going to
connect the actions or the affordances
to the policy
actions or affordances are things that
can happen in a single time step
policies are sequences of multiple time
steps in
length so it's basically like saying
each policy was evaluated so time Step n
and then
um each policy is described in terms of
what actions it contains finally a soft
Max temperature parameter Theta sub
Alpha is applied to account for
Randomness or shaky handedness in
Behavior not accounted for by the
model so this is kind of just brought up
here but it's explored more in other
papers um when the soft when the softmax
is
one your behavior is sampled directly
from your policy
posterior that's matching
behavior when the soft Max is very
high then you select
the best
behavior even if it's only slightly
better and then if your soft Max is very
low it basically erases differences in
the posterior likelihood of
action okay so so Daniel this this uh
it's new parameter is not needed in the
um in the active inference model right
it's only needed when we
um when we do this parameter estimation
right when we compute the likelihood
function right I mean the core active
inference model is very sparse it
doesn't contain learning or attention or
shaky hand so the textbook is showing us
all these different
motifs none of them which you have to do
but if your phenomena of interest is
captured by this type of behavior this
is a useful
Motif but it's not like any of them are
being required for us to do in all
situations it's just saying this is one
kind of um structural
model that can capture decision-making
Behavior okay
okay but you're you're right like
previous examples didn't have
this right right I I also would like to
clarify the policy you just mentioned
there so so
policy
um you said the policy specifies
actions uh at each time point if we
think about the discret time model right
um so it simply says that know what
action I would take at time one what
action I would take a Time
two
um yep here I just went to the ontology
just looked up policy it's a sequence of
actions okay I wonder because in in my
area where I think about policy as a as
a mapping from state to
action uh not simply from time to action
so you're you're thinking about about
you know polies in time one what I do in
time two what I do uh in general uh a
policy defined as in if in certain State
what I should I do time just is one
dimension of the
states um is this a a special feature of
active inference or is a it's something
like consistent with the other like
Dynamic uh process
it's more similar than not to how policy
selection is discussed in reinforcement
learning deep Q learning because
fundamentally we're talking about action
selection so it's overwhelmingly more
similar than
not but yes there are some slight
differences because here we're only
talking about policies as sequences of
action through time and then using other
features of the model like other state
um inferences of the model to update our
posterior on
policy but we're we're not we're not
making
policy explicitly a function
of other states other than
time
yeah it's generally the same control
theory setting with just a slightly
different setup but but you you you
should document what is meant by policy
in that setting pull out the quote or
pull out how it's meant and then let's
just just toose it side by side and then
it'll be
clear right in control theory in general
the policies is the action is function
not only the time but also the system
States
right
that's right the sequences of actions
are a function of parameters the model
and a sequence of
stimuli that's
here the likelihood of the
parameters is describing the sequence of
actions Through
Time conditioned upon parameters model
and
observations
we can go more into it but it's it's
it's the same setting of inferring
actions from other features of the
model okay so what you what you observes
are this actions
okay
yeah um here here's Us in the behavioral
laboratory observing U Tilda the object
empirical behavior of the system of
Interest objective here it's a objective
meaning
empirical like what we objectively
measured and recorded
empirically in our
laboratory so what we recorded as data
is the output of the subject of our
behavioral
experiment so this isn't taking on the
the the the philosophy of you know
objective and subjective and all this
this is just a behavioral
setup here's the rat that's our
behavioral subject it has a cognitive
Model A generative
model and we're observing Its Behavior
and that is being used as our empirical
scientific
data for cognitive modeling
so o is also input by the uh
experimental designer by the
um so it's it's given kind of a
parameter right the
stimuli yeah the experimental stimuli is
a action by the
experimenter and a sensory State for the
subject
yeah I think that the the key here that
utia is the output of the experiment the
behavioral experiment uh and the input
of the the fitting process that gives
you the
Theta once you have done the measurement
UA you can guess which parameter is the
is the best one to describe this
vavle right right yeah here is the G
action to find the best parameter theeta
right this what the uh or it's the
purpose Theta is the
parameters
um so so the other question I have
actually in this figure 9.1 is what is
m so it seems M just the model all the
parameters of the
model then why why do we use like
different symbols one use M another use
Theta M for the generative model of the
of the subject and Theta for the
experimental
parameters okay for example in the T
example chapter seven what is M and what
is what is Theta what are the
differences M would be the parameters
that describe the cognitive model of the
Rat Theta for the parameters describing
the setup of the teamas like the idea
that 50% of the time the food is over
here or that when the food is here it
has a 99% probability of
reward okay so M basically represents
other parameters
not uh this is just a schema you know
this is just saying yes this it's you
don't have to use exactly this one and
only basian
graph so it's just saying whatever is
the subjective model you can struct
is you're going to be conditioning upon
the experimental parameters and the
cognitive model
parameters okay exper um so Theta is
experiment experimental parameters so
those are the parameters that we are
interested in right and they might be
some of the ones you're interested
in
but different Laboratories are
interested in different questions some
might have a very trivial subjective
model and be interested in doing
inference up here other times this might
be fixed up here and there might be
something interesting
here may I interject a question yeah
yeah okay so so Daniel something I I
been thinking about about that's this is
more of a philosophical question
but I really like this
representation uh I just wondered if it
matters in the free energy principle
approach to be worried about
nested cognitive
systems um because in the work that I'm
doing nestedness is uh for the system
that I'm describing there are subsystems
so we have a system within another
system within another
system so from a very abstract point of
view the nestedness is that not relevant
because at every boundary you're just
dealing with a different set of sensory
input from something else so it doesn't
matter if you're messing anything you're
just a system and you can model the
behaviors of that system
separately from the fact that it's
receiving input the inputs are coming
from multiple levels of higher order
that affect it does that make
sense yeah I
mean nested models are are naturally
amenable to this type of modeling okay
so here's a nest an example of a nested
model so here like we we see this kind
of figure 4.3 generative model
shape um now that that like e downstairs
like a downward facing e that's like the
sense making component and then the
upstairs with a policy selection so now
that is kind of expanded so that each
Leaf of the E has another nested
e and so there's nothing in active
inference that says that systems must be
nested
however it is very amenable to modeling
Collective lateral interactions within a
level and then having nested models
across levels and then just briefly two
kinds of nested models that we see
sometimes the nested model refers to an
actual spatial enclosure so you know a
continent and then a region within a
continent and then a village within the
region um with like slower and bigger
things being at higher levels but also
we see nested models for
metacognition where you have higher
levels of
metacognition as nested observers and
and top- Down actors of lower level of
cognition so it's not spatially
enclosing but it could be thought of as
like a cognitive
enclosure I understand that yes that
that was very helpful thank you uh but
so let me see if I can ask this a little
this is very abstract but um is it the
case that even so even when we're
looking at those nested
models um The Nest the sub models the
the ones that are nested within a
bigger uh
model there are there any modeling
issues that you need to add to to your
subsystem in order to take into account
that it's receiving sens uh inputs from
multiple higher
order
systems or does it or you just U from a
modeling perspective it doesn't matter
you just look at yes they look
identical in principle it's well
behaved in practice the challenge is
that nested models get very very large
very quickly
so then it it's like well you know I
mean you know the pancreas is nest in
the liver and the liver and the chest
and the person and the family and it's
like all of a sudden you're just with a
model with with millions of degrees of
freedom with limited data sets so a and
yet making a a appropriately articulated
nested model actually can help the model
embody the structure of the world which
uses the data more effectively
so um a smartly constructed nested model
will help you make the best of the data
you have but a sort of nested model
construction as a fishing
Expedition ends up losing
interpretability even if it ends up
recapitulating real
features um yes so no that that's that
thank you that was super helpful because
actually so one of the boundar Aries to
just to give an example one of the
boundaries that I'm working with is the
boundary between or or thinking about um
the the human body and um the human body
under conditions of our early
evolutionary adaptedness
environment and what's really
interesting about humans is that we have
this
um um brain got aess cyc
neuroimmunological sophisticated system
that has a very uh well documented
effect on the
brain uh when uh the immune system is
reacting to a pathogen so it sends
signals to the brain and causes what's
called um sness Behavior right so that's
an example of communication that
we understand that's going on between
subsystems and the
Brain um but we actually can talk about
the communication the way that the
communication is happening so you don't
have to be doing a fishing
Expedition um you you know eventually I
would like to be able to model those
relationships in some way yeah that's a
great transition actually to what um
Andrew um brought up last week so like
since we're in chapter
nine um you know we we're talking about
the empirical data but but the book only
has limited amount of empirical data but
it
cites um heavily these other studies but
then Andrew suggested that we go into
this one so I mean Andrew what what did
you want to discuss about this paper I
pulled out some of the the um figures
that we can talk about but what do you
want to talk about
it sure um see I had a limited amount of
time available between last week and
this week but the the initial thought
was um just kind of because this chapter
lays out kind of a series of steps that
one could follow as a sort of recipe um
the idea was maybe we
could um identify in in layman's term
well as far as we can in layman's terms
like um something like what are what are
those steps as played out like for
example in this paper here um
yeah so we kind of have like we can
match like to each step of the recipe
provided like maybe what's going on here
right awesome yeah so chapter six we
constructed the generative model um here
and these are all like steps that have
to happen but this isn't exactly needing
to happen this order but chapter six we
basically construct the um generative
model that's step two and it's
Associated likely Ood function which is
just the function of behavior being
emitted conditioned upon parameters
observations in the generative model
like just that we talked about with 9.2
and then we collect data we crunch it
all together invert the basian model and
then do statistics on the outcome so
let's see what it looks like in um the
case of Ryan Smith at all's work on gut
inference so they develop aasian
computational model for gastrointestinal
in interoception so this is not exactly
like the microbiome neurotransmitter
slower time scale interaction but this
is the faster like vagal nerve
mediated interception with the
gastrointestinal um so it was completed
by healthy individuals they were
undergoing EEG so there was getting
neuro neuroimaging data
and peripheral physiological recording
like C like some measures of the body
and then this I also found this kind of
interesting these self-report questions
how hungry do you feel how you know how
difficult was this task this is just
showing like you can assess a variety of
physiological measures self-report
measures these are all
data okay okay another important thing
that that to keep in mind is like it's
not about constructing the one
generative model it's about having a
portfolio of related generative models
that do and don't have different
components and then you kind of test
across them um like when they talked
about what are the two reasons to do
cognitive modeling one of them was if
you have a fixed generative model then
you can look for group differences
another one is from the data set you can
identify which models are appropriate so
here these 12 models differ kind of
combinatorically in their different
features so standard statistical
modeling technique test for you know
just Mo factor a just Factor B A and B
together A and B and C just C and D
together so so that's what they they're
going to um do and in table one they
Define the same ontology terms that we
see in the
textbook um here's the
test they swallow this
pill that vibrates in their stomach and
then they signal whether they did or
didn't perceive
it so the true
State hidden state
is whether it vibrated or not that's
known because that's controlled by the
experimenter
um and then the observations are the
perception that they
experience obviously if it was a fully
observable situation you'd have like the
a matrix would be an identity Matrix you
would just
simply be able to perceive it but
there's some intensity of signal
where what they're going to test is that
well it turns out that it's not 100%
perceived but also it's not 0% perceived
and maybe there are interesting patterns
of people's
perception here is literally where we
see the basian graph now this is a model
that doesn't
include action because the person is not
in control of vibrating this little
thing so we only are seeing the
downstairs part of the model so in that
way it's
um much like the early example in
chapter
7 so this was the music listening
example in chapter 7 just the
downstairs the prior hidden State
Through Time observations at each time
step but no upstairs action selection
component
prior hidden State on the actual
vibration observations whether it's
perceived a is the mapping between
vibration State and observation B is how
it's transformed so that model could be
specified ahead of time you could
pre-register the study so you kind of
know that you want that and then they
describe this a lot more in the
caption um
they also
describe yeah so then they do some
descriptive statistics on this
model the interceptive
Precision so that's the Precision of the
a matrix if the a matrix is just the
identity matrix it's the most precise
that means that you have perfect
observation if the a matrix was low
Precision it was just a wash you
wouldn't be able to perceive anything
and then it could be anything
between um prior beliefs favoring the
presence of a vibration PV that's the
D
variable and then the learning rate is
describing the the rate of change on
B so those are not simply descriptive
features of the empirical data if you
just wanted to say who's has a higher
accuracy or who's more right or
something you could just summarize the
data you wouldn't even need to do
cognitive
modeling then they look at all of these
different empirical
patterns so here on the columns these
are
um Prima fascia components of the
behavioral study these are just
descriptive
outcomes from what empirically did
happen like the true positive negative
rate and the reaction time
patterns on the rows are these cognitive
parameters that again they identified
with their model so features of their
model map not the territory and yet
there are still these interesting
patterns um then they they can do
different
conditions and show that their the
cognitive parameters that they're in
interested in that those cognitive
parameters are variable in different
settings here they look at the the
cognitively inferred parameters on the
rows and then a a uh
self-report and some kind of like um
personal data aent
BMI um just like other scientific
studies like the kind of result result
is like a point estimate and a variance
so you can say some of these results are
significant at different
thresholds now they're going to connect
the cognitive model parameter to
EEG
Dynamics here they look at clust string
of erps event related potentials so
these are kind of like dynamical
patterns in the EEG over different time
scales and then they can cluster
different regions by the similarity of
their response and look at how
those kind of traveling waves are
related to
um uh those traveling waves the erps are
related to those different cognitive
modeling
parameters
and they do that for other brain regions
too me then D can I ask a question
yeah the the um corination Matrix showed
uh sorry the before with the learning
rate is Nar rate estimated from the uh
experimental
data yes everything is estimated from
the data in this
paper okay
okay so so how how do they construct the
magn function to do the estimation we
use the um EG data to to
estimate I mean you look look at the
paper for
more details but
um the EEG data are being taken as kind
of
like
this is you know what you see is what
you get here right there's no EEG here
there's just a prior on vibration and
then an an observation and then the
mapping between the observation and the
vibration or not so that's kind of like
the core phenomena that they're studying
and then they have the age and the BMI
and the EEG and the
self-report so then those other data are
kind of
overlaid on the timeline of this kind of
core model and then you can look for
correlations
[Music]
between
um this graph and the
EEG so I don't think you need to take in
the likelihood of the EEG data
specifically well but in order to
estimate at the learning
rate they do need a MAG function right
so it has just parameter of this activ
inference
model yeah I mean we can look for for
more details on how the learning rate is
calculated but they describe it in that
caption I mean
it's it's described but yeah look into
it and see if that's how you would
describe learning rate and these are
features of the map not the
territory so again it's common for
people to look at this and then
reference some feature of the
world but it's not about referencing
some feature of the world to validate or
invalidate this model it's about
generating a portfolio of models that
have different
features and then propagating that
portfolio of models
forwards and then saying actually
learning rate does matter because the
one that had it versus the one that
didn't had this better
fit and someone says oh but you didn't
think about this and you go okay cool
now let's add model 13 with that
feature and that's the real that's the
Delight of the empirical
conversation just people bring things up
and it's like okay either we have
explored it and we can talk about the
impact of that variable or we haven't
considered it yet so then thank you for
the suggestion let's add it in and then
come back to it and that's the iterated
modeling
process but yeah here by looking at the
table how how do we how do we know which
model is a better
description um so you have 12 models to
yeah yeah yeah great question they they
describe this the most common method
used is the basian information Criterion
Bic or the related um
AIC um the Bic criteria basically um
rewards fitting a model uh fitting the
data well and it penalizes having extra
parameters and so because you're all
every model with another parameter you
will always get a better fit like a
principal component analysis the next
principal component all always is going
to soak up more
variants so make the best fitting model
is actually a kind
of
[Music]
um ironically useless singular goal but
if you say I want the model to be at the
optimal tradeoff where like the
parameters are like punching above their
weight so that's usually how people
select it but that's not the only model
selection imperative you might say
I'm okay with having a huge model I just
want the most accurate one so then you
might take one that has more parameters
or you might say I don't need the most
accurate one I need it to just be better
than
50% and I need it to you know fit on an
index
card yes there isn't an answer in the
general case for which model you should
select and you might want to actually
just hold the whole portfolio and just
keep that whole distribution that's like
Ensemble
modeling yeah so so I'm just wondering
why it doesn't show the selection
criteria in the table when they
selection
criteria yeah yeah so the BC they didn't
show us right um well not in that table
like I I mean I the the models are
compared in some formal way but in that
image they're just they're just listing
which ones they are but yeah it could
have included like the likelihood of the
Bic for the models or the number of
parameters
um it's just not shown in that
representation maybe in the supplement
or maybe somewhere else but but yeah
that that's usually what is shown you
see like it will be like model one and
it will be like Delta Bic Z and then it
will show how how much behind in the Bic
the other ones
are um and then if we were studying an
active setting like let's just say that
now we're in a little modified version
where the person can make can be in the
you know red or the orange
room and they can move between those two
rooms and then those two rooms have like
a different probability of the stomach
thing vibrating so now there's some
policy
variable well that's the power of the
base graph it's just another parameter
to
estimate so the same ex and then someone
says well what about having a policy on
the air conditioning as well then you
add the air conditioning policy oh and
now we want the observations not just to
be the interception now we want to have
like you know exter reception too you
just keep composing and building the
models but in chapter nine that's where
we make the contact with the
empirical and that kind of like reminder
that there are real
things to
study and that you can design the
generative model ahead of time and then
do the
experiment and then just as soon as you
collect the data you just dump it into
the generative model and you basically
have your paper ready that's one great
option another option is the data have
already been collected and you know what
structure they are and then you can
construct a generative model that will
load in that
structure so whether the data are
collected before or after obviously it's
it's different
scientifically but in both cases this
chapter gets us to the point
where we can take in data bring it into
this kind of
format but then in the end we make the
kind of bar bar plots and time series
and correlation matrices that we would
see like from literally any other
scientific paper
yeah what what did anyone think about
this well I'm just kind of stepping back
and I wanted to uh ask
you uh so is a lot of the literature
that
on recent literature on the energy
principle about you know when we going
to the empirical world is figuring
out or trying to infert what generative
models different
systems have in order for us to be able
to begin to test hypothesis from the
free energy
prot
that's a great question yeah definitely
like one line of research or multiple
lines of research are related to the
fundamental physics of cognition some
lines of research are more computational
capacity
building and so they're interested in
like motifs and comp computational
implementations another set of research
that's more empirically oriented is
looking at empirical data and developing
cognitive
models that's one direction of
empiricism and then the other direction
of empiricism is with the cognitive
model in hand looking at differences
amongst individuals or
groups and like Ryan Smith ated all's
work has both of those directions of
empiricism sometimes um like in this
paper they're taking a simple setting
and then they're exploring a range of
cognitive
models in other settings they're
basically taking a cognitive model
identified from previous work or however
and then asking okay do individuals with
these different diagnoses differ for
example and those those two directions
of empiricism can coexist in one paper
but but then it's kind of like this
joint identification of what should the
model be but then how do the individuals
differ in the
model and here's those two reasons that
they
say computational
phenotyping with the model in hand
describing
individuals or
with the data in
hand ask which model you want to
utilize Daniel can can I ask you a
question here
yeah about T's example um in chapter
seven the textbook provides a complete
example about the uh active influence
model
and in this
chapter um they also talk about that t
example but I wonder if there is any
empirical data about the the mouse you
know movement and that can we can like
you know use the same example to
illustrate the the basic steps and idea
in chapter
nine yeah I mean it's a great
question something I've wondered about
too don't we have like hundreds of
thousands of data points on the
teamas I don't know what data set that
is but but these are experiments that
have been
done here those are simulated data not
the experimented
data right yeah here they just were
using the teamas in the synthetic
Direction but yeah it's a great project
to find an empirical data set
um and then you would need to make the
generative model for it because it
wouldn't be exactly
this but this structure might work
well but yeah I mean this is the work
that I hope that the textbook gets us
all to is going to behavioral settings
and studies that have been done and
building generative
model but this is literally the work
that we have to
do
well you're you're not aware of anyone
have done it right because I I asked a
few people who who uh extend this uh
teamas uh
example and but none of them have done
empirical um study and
estimate The Motto
parameters I've never seen it with like
the mammal Tas again even though they're
they're are actually probably thousands
of data sets on the Tas so I think
that's a a very viable
option perhaps people use the teamas
because it's easy to make a point about
epistemic value but usually the teamas
isn't the case that people are
interested in
studying but if it were a lab that were
studying decision making or addiction or
learning in
rodents then they would be actually
looking to do a cognitive model with the
teamas so that's where the collaboration
between people with active inference
expertise and domain
experts and then you have an iterated
modeling process with
[Music]
them are all the features included in
this model and the back and forth
there and then find out what the
generative
model what kind of empirical insights
you can
have and in that case if it's already a
data set that's collected in a published
paper that's the perfect setting because
then you can say here's what active
inference goes beyond descriptive
statistics and what it actually what
value it does add to the
setting yeah
yeah there's a lot of Behavioral data
sets to do this
on yeah if you were actually looking for
data sets I mean there's a great um the
busak labs there's um Yori rousaki
neuroscientist at NYU he has an entire
lab dedicated
to um things like for example studying
like mice and and rats are kind of his
expertise and um you know running many
experiments where they're trying to use
um electrophysiological data to track uh
what is going on in mice what's going on
in their their neurons whenever they're
navigating a maze and it's where they do
research on things like um Place cells
and all these fascinating things where
if you draw out a topological map out of
the EEG data you can actually see like
the the the mouse is tracking where it
is location
so I see Daniel's point to bring it back
that there are many experiments done
that highly relate to the tas's example
but I guess it's around there that you
could have collaboration between someone
who's an expert in active inference
versus those who carry out these kinds
of experiments to test the data that's
already been collected uh but within
more of active inference kind of framing
because because the the the lab
technician here at busak or otherwise
are attempting to understand something
more like the neurobiology but they're
not necessarily getting too indepth with
the cognitive modeling aspect or the
kinds of questions that someone um doing
research in active inference might be
asking that's my thought on that
right yeah thanks
angel
so
um this is a uh this is a question that
is bugging me and I just want to bring
it up now um before I get really deep
into all the material which is um when
working with human
subjects uh you know one of the things
that that that I see as a is it's always
been a huge problem in out my research
is that as soon as you enter into the
interview
setting that in itself you know it has a
huge observer effect so so from the
perspective of active inference you're
dealing with the fact that this
individual from whom you're getting some
information about their generative model
in their heads they have a generative
model in their heads about that
interaction and making and already
trying to make assumptions or thinking
about what is this interviewer going to
ask me and what are their expectations
because that's what we humans do and so
if you could tell me early on where in
this world of active influence is that
addressed because it's a huge issue in
in my systems in the systems that I work
with
yeah it's a big question there's a lot
lot of pieces to say on it okay um
suffice to say that studying like a
pendulum is an easier active system
than study an active system that has
theory of
mindly okay thank you thank you that was
like really well but so yeah it's not to
be
found in this image but this image is
kind of like yeah pointing towards it
okay yeah thank you to the textbook
group
um we return for chapter 10 next time
okay thank you very much take care bye
bye